Hello and welcome to
the Rediscovering JavaScript course.
Today, we want to talk about what
JavaScript is and what it has become.
The problem with JavaScript
is that it's always been a thing
that a lot of people wanted to do
and only a few people have been
very enthusiastic about.
You probably have been dabbling
with JavaScript or you've been writing JavaScript,
but most of the time
you will have used other people's code.
When JavaScript came around,
it was just something that we added into websites
and we learned by looking
at other people's code.
The view source was our teacher
and we actually looked at what was going on,
copied and pasted code from somebody else,
changed a few numbers around,
hoped nothing broke,
and then we actually had a
JavaScript that was our own.
This has changed a lot.
If you've been using JavaScript
for quite some while and you go back
into the world right now
and you realise that people talk
about things like NPM,
like Node, like Webpack,
the language seems to be
much more complex than it used to be.
It used to be more like Java,
Ruby, or these kind of languages.
And I want you to understand that
this is normal and this is a normal evolution
and you don't have to
feel inadequate about it,
you don't have to feel worried about it,
it just means that the
versatility of JavaScript itself
made it possible for it to go
in two different directions.
So when you become a JavaScript developer
nowadays, you could be anything.
You could be just a web developer
that does some beautiful things
on websites with JavaScript,
you could be a Node developer
who builds servers, API's, micro-services,
all these kind of cool things,
or you could be even
a hardcore app developer
that builds something like
Slack or Atom in the JavaScript,
HTML, and CSS, and then
packages it up as an application itself.
Now if you think back what
JavaScript used to be,
you will get into a lot
of resources online
that are very, very outdated
and very very dangerous to learn nowadays.
Take for example w3schools here,
which is always the first result in Google
when you google
something random in JavaScript.
It teaches you a lot of ways how JavaScript
used to be back in the days
and and some of the JavaScript syntax
that was back in the days.
But a lot of this JavaScript is not how
you write things nowadays anymore.
As somebody who's been
using these resources for years,
we have a few hang-ups
that we should get rid of.
One of the hang-ups is that browsers
will always be terrible
and browsers will always be in our way
and not supporting the
things that we want to do.
Another hang-up is that our end users
will not upgrade their environments
and will have a problem with
new features that we want to have.
We should free ourselves from
these hang-ups and from these fears,
and that's why we need new resources
to learn JavaScript and to find new information.
So if you want to look up something nowadays
in JavaScript, there's a a few resources
I want to quickly go
through with you to play with.
These are the things where
you should always go to
if you want to find out something new,
and they're always up to date
because they're community driven environments.
So when JavaScript
became a thing,
a lot of people stopped
writing JavaScript itself
because browsers were problematic –
like Internet Explorer, Netscape,
whatever, Firefox, later on Opera.
All of them had different ways of dealing
with the language because the language
was not properly standardised as well.
And we had no web standards
before that time as well.
When the web standard movement came around
and HTML5 became a thing, that changed drastically.
Our resources nowadays,
our browsers nowadays are standards-based
and agree with each other
what different technologies should be used
and what becomes a standard
and what doesn't.
We don't have to run after the innovation
of browser makers anymore
and do things for one browser
and differently for another browser.
And that is a wonderful thing.
One of the main things
that people used to do
is use jQuery instead of JavaScript
because jQuery helped us
to level the playing field,
to actually give the browsers
the same experiences,
and we didn't have
to think about these anymore.
But nowadays, browsers are so good
and the standards have been going so far,
that you most likely don't need jQuery anymore
because you're actually adding extra code
for an environment
that doesn't exist anymore
and for browsers that
shouldn't be in use anymore.
The first resource I want
you to get excited about
because, I'm very excited
about it, is called caniuse.com.
caniuse.com is a resource site
that tells you what
browsers can do these days
and which browsers support
which feature in what format.
The most common use case
for caniuse.com is that you will go there
to find about support for something,
say for example, the fetch API.
Once you type that in, you already get
the results telling you what fetch is,
a modern replacement
for XMLHttpRequest,
and which browsers support it.
You can also see the red browsers
that don't support it
and sometimes there are yellow browsers
that support it but have problems.
Once there are any problems,
it will be listed with known issues here
where you can work around them.
In this case, we don't have any.
But other features might have them.
So you know where the problems are,
when they will be fixed, and what's happening.
The other thing that for
every feature that you look up,
you will have a resources tab here
that show you about the specification,
having a demo, going for polyfill,
and then have the different platforms
like Internet Explorer, Edge, Chrome,
Firefox, and WebKit, and seeing when
they have been shipping it or what
the problem with the status is right now.
So, if you always wonder
about having a new feature
that somebody's excited
about and you wonder
if you can use it in
your products with your end-users,
this is a great resource to look at.
It's continuously maintained.
All the browser makers are giving feedback
to the maintainers of this product.
So this is where to learn if it's safe to
use something
and also get excited about using it.
If you want to know about
the language JavaScript itself –
So that's for the hardcore
nerds about JavaScript –
the TC39 ECMA group is actually
the people who write the language.
This is the consortium
or this is the technical committee
that creates the next
version of that language
and maintains the current
version of that language.
So this is the main source
for the language itself,
not some other resource
that might be saying, like,
we know JavaScript.
These are the people who make it.
If you want to look up something in JavaScript,
and you want to go and see, like,
"How does something work?"
The MDN Web Docs, to me,
are the best resource.
They're not the best resource
because I used to work for Mozilla,
but this is because where
all the browser makers
realised they should
put their information.
The MDN Web Docs is an open wiki.
So you can edit it, you can you can take part
in this community as well, and you will –
and you will see features that get updated
much faster than any
other resource out there.
So if you look up something like,
for example array map, in this case,
you will not only get
an example of what it is,
but you will get all kinds
of information about what it means.
So it explains to you that the map method
creates a new array with the results
of calling a provided function
and so on and so forth.
You can run these examples live here,
you can then reset them to undo them as well,
and then you get detailed information
about the syntax of it, how to use map,
and how to use the callbacks.
You have a listing of the specifications
explaining what different things mean,
and you also have
a browser compatibility table
listed in here which is, weirdly enough,
coming from caniuse.com.
So these two sites are tightly linked.
So this information will always
be up-to-date as well.
If you want to know about the different browsers
and how they work with JavaScript,
you're in luck as well.
Back in the days when I started
as a JavaScript developer,
these were black holes.
Nobody knew what was coming,
nobody knew what was going on.
Nowadays, all browsers have resources
and even Twitter accounts
where you find new
information about them.
This is the Microsoft one for Edge.
For Chrome, there's a Chromium blog,
for Safari, there's the WebKit blog,
for Firefox, there's,
of course, the Firefox blog,
and for others, like
Samson browser, Opera browser,
all browser makers are very open to developers,
to talk to them and go for it.
So these are some
of the resources to look at
when you want to start working
with JavaScript nowadays.
These are up-to-date resources,
editable resources, where you can take part
and you can make them
better if you want to.
Don't just randomly Google
for problems in JavaScript,
then copy and paste the code,
take those resources and learn JavaScript
from the makers of JavaScript
and from the implementers of JavaScript
and you will be a much happier developer.
So now you know some
of the resources that you can keep revisiting
and learning that JavaScript
is not what it used to be.
In the next video, we're
going to talk about some
of the features that
JavaScript is doing nowadays
or some of the implementations
that JavaScript has that you might not
have been thinking about
and you haven't seen before.
=======================
==   CLOSED CAPTIONS   ==
== BY YERKCOL PTY LTD ==
=======================