Hello. I'm Chris Heilmann.
I'm from Berlin, Germany and I've been
a web developer for over 20 years.
And ever since we had JavaScript,
that was one of my passions.
I wrote a few books about it,
I did a lot of trainings on it,
and today, I'm going
to share some of that with you.
I'm very excited that our web community
has become so big that you can go to Meetups
or conferences almost every week –
and that's what I do.
I give a lot of keynotes,
I give a lot of trainings,
and I interview in companies
and with companies,
what they want to do
with the newest technologies.
That includes machine learning,
artificial intelligence,
and also good old web development
with JavaScript and other languages.
This course is for people who want
to understand JavaScript
and want to use it now
and are kind of overwhelmed
by all the offers that are there
and the fragmentation
of the learning materials
that are out there.
So, if you're somebody
who's just starting with JavaScript,
that's for you as well.
Or if you're somebody
who's been doing JavaScript
but feels like there should be more,
that's for you as well.
It's a good overview of what
the JavaScript space is doing nowadays
and what you can do with the language,
and it's much more than
it used to be in the past.
All of the materials and all of the products
we're going to talk about in this course
are web-based and open-source,
so you can work with them across platforms.
You don't need to have a Macintosh.
You don't need to have a Windows machine.
You can use whatever you want.
I don't want to tell you
what environment to use
and what environment to set up.
Instead, you should find the one
that makes you most comfortable.
So, nothing here is something
that you need to buy because open-source
helps us be much better as developers.
I hope you find something
that will excite you and you will become
a better JavaScript developer
after the end of this course.
So let's get going.
=======================
==   CLOSED CAPTIONS   ==
== BY YERKCOL PTY LTD ==
=======================