Welcome to this video in the
Rediscovering JavaScript series.
In this section, I want you
to remember that JavaScript is huge
and there's all kind of things
that are done with JavaScript.
So you shouldn't feel bad
if you feel overwhelmed looking
around what people are doing with it.
You should also not feel bad
that other people are better at it
because other people do different things.
So when it comes to using
JavaScript these days,
it's not about knowing everything.
That's almost impossible to do
because the different ways JavaScript
are implemented around the web
and around technology stacks
ask for different ways of learning
JavaScript and different ways of using it.
So something that makes
sense in an old environment
does not necessarily make sense
on the web and the other way around.
So if you're a JavaScript developer
that just wants to use vanilla JavaScript,
basically, JavaScript without
any add-ons, without any features,
without any datasets around it
or toolsets around it,
MDN Web Docs is where
you're actually gonna be living.
This is where you find the information,
and this is where you find excitement,
and this is probably a community
where you also want to join
and you also want to be part of.
So there, you can shine, there,
you can give your information back,
and there, you can do what you're
actually excited about and what you can do.
If you're more inclined to use JavaScript
in a way to build proper software services
or servers or these kind of things,
then the Node world is where
you're much more excited.
These different worlds in JavaScript
all have their different communities,
have their different Slack channels,
have their different events,
and have their different
community gatherings.
So sometimes you're standing
as a web developer at a Node event.
You don't understand a single word.
Whereas like a Node developer
goes to a design conference
and doesn't understand what people
are excited about when they do so many
different things in JavaScript
in the Node environment.
So make sure that you find
a spot that you're excited about
and then concentrate on that one.
But don't look at the others
who are doing things in different ways
and think that they're doing it wrong.
They're just doing it
differently than you do.
There's also nothing wrong
with taking a different approach
to developing by using a library.
React is a huge community
and a huge environment
also based on JavaScript,
but React itself is a language
that does things completely differently
than browsers do it
and vanilla JavaScript does it.
This doesn't mean that you're
actually giving up on the course,
that you're actually not
becoming a JavaScript developer,
it means that you're taking a shortcut
or you're taken away to build bigger applications
different applications –
on a different stack.
So look at these things and look around
where you will find yourself interested.
You can stay with the vanilla JavaScript world
and build everything yourself,
you can go to a server-side environment
with Node, or you can use Vue.js, Angular,
or React to build applications in that stack,
much like we used to have people
writing things in jQuery rather than JavaScript
because jQuery back then solved
the problem of browser differences.
React and Vue and Angular
and those solve other problems
by putting architectural ideas
of software development
into the JavaScript space.
So none of these things
should a barrier for you.
None of these things
should make you feel bad.
But understand that if you're
a JavaScript expert,
you will probably not
understand React from the get-go.
You have to put effort in
and learn it that way.
The same way with Vue.js.
A lot of designers like Vue.js
because it's much easier than vanilla JavaScript.
Because every time we talk
about vanilla JavaScript,
we talk about all the exceptions
that you have to worry about.
With Vue.js, a lot of these things
have been evened out for you
so you can start developing
something pretty and beautiful
simpler than by
understanding the language itself.
So think about JavaScript again
as a "pick and mix", as something
where you can go and you don't
have to play in all these communities –
but you should pick one of them
and become excited in those.
So I hope you feel a bit calmer
and you have a bit of a Zen feeling
about JavaScript right now
knowing that you don't need to play
in all the parts and understand
everything that's going on around you.
In the next video, we're going to talk
about the development environment
for JavaScript, which changed drastically
from just being a text editor in a browser.
So I want you to understand
where to play, what to do, and what to install.