Welcome back to
Rediscovering JavaScript.
This time, I want to talk about
how our development environment
changed over the last few years
and some of the things you might not
be using already but you should
to make yourself much more effective.
There's always a bit of a
weird thing telling people, like,
"You need to learn this to be more
effective and feels like a lot of work".
But some of the things I'm going to
show you right now are so common
and are so useful that it actually
makes no sense not to use them.
We were always super-excited
as JavaScript developers that all we needed
was a text editor and the browser
to execute our JavaScript in.
This has changed with JavaScript
now being different than it was before.
And also the environments that
we use have changed immensely.
The first thing to think about
is how browsers have changed.
Browsers are not the black holes
any longer where we don't know
what's happening and how much
support they have for JavaScript.
It's also almost impossible nowadays
to turn off JavaScript in a browser.
It was much easier for users
back in the day to do so.
But we have a problem in browsers
nowadays as people that have add-ons
like ad blockers and these kind of things
that might block your JavaScript.
But as users themselves,
people are much more okay
with JavaScript being active in the
browsers and most of them don't even know it.
All browsers are nowadays evergreen,
so they're actually coming up every two days,
every two weeks, every month,
sometimes it's up to three months
for a new version to come out.
But it's not like the four or five years
that we used to have between different versions
of Internet Explorer, and people didn't upgrade.
So upgrading their browsers is much,
much easier than it used to be,
and that means, for us as
JavaScript developers,
we have new features to play with.
Every browser also comes
with developer tools built in.
So this, for example – here's Firefox.
And if I type the inspect element,
I can see I've got my HTML editor,
I've got a debugger where
I can debug my JavaScript
and we're going
to come back to that later.
I've got style editors.
I've got all kinds of network insights
and performance insights for my applications.
And I have a console in there.
So if you want to just try out
some JavaScript, you can use that
to actually write JavaScript
and do like: 3 + 2
which is math, not JavaScript.
But JavaScript editor
now shows you this is 5.
The next thing that browsers have –
all of them have developer tools.
So there's Firefox, of course,
with the Firefox tools.
There's Chrome with the
Chromium dev tools,
which probably are the ones
that are the most
sophisticated ones at the moment.
Edge has the F12 Dev Tools
which are much better than people think
because we haven't looked at them for years.
And even Safari has some
really good developer tools in there.
But you need to turn it into
a developer mode first
to show these developer tools.
Mobile browsers don't necessarily
have developer tools,
but a lot of them allow you to connect
from your desktop to your mobile phone
to debug the browser
in these developer tools as well.
So all browsers over the last few years
have become not only ways
to display and execute JavaScript
but also development environments
to build JavaScript in
and to write JavaScript in.
The next step that we have
is that we replaced the normal text messaging
or the text editors that we have
with more sophisticated editors.
We're going to go into detail later on
as to what that means
and what benefits a good editor
has for you, but suffice it to say,
a lot of them are hackable
and that's the best thing about them.
These editors are written in languages
that we can write ourselves –
we can extend them with extensions
or we can write – be part of the main code
because all of them are open-source.
So our development environments,
our editor environments have become
ways for us to contribute
rather than just hoping that an editor
will have a certain feature
and us jumping from editor to editor
and having to learn all the different features
of them to become more effective in using them.
The next thing that a lot of people
are afraid of and wondering why
we should be using it is the terminal.
The terminal, in this case here –
it's now indistinct on my OSX machine
or on my Windows machine,
I've got the Ubuntu shell as well –
is basically a UNIX shell.
So it's going back to 1970's technologies
and we always, as JavaScript developers,
wondered why we would ever need this.
People who wrote server-side technologies
like Java, PHP, Perl were much more efficient
in those things and used to know them already.
We didn't think there was a necessity there.
With Node, that changed.
Node is JavaScript
that runs on the server side,
so everything you need to know
and you need to run Node in
happens in the terminal.
That also means that a lot of JavaScript tools
like build processes, package managing,
and so on and so forth
happens in the terminal itself.
So it's a good skill to have.
It's not too hard to learn the terminal.
It feels a bit weird at times
and sometimes you do a Node request
and you get, like, five screens
of random error messages
and you don't know what's happening,
but don't get discouraged by that.
What you can do in the terminal
and what you do as a JavaScript developer
in the terminal is use build tools,
use these scripts, use Node environments,
but also do your version controlling,
and we're gonna have a special in-depth video
later on on version controlling
and what it means to you
and why it's a beneficial thing.
So the terminal is
something good to know.
It's not necessary
you have to be an expert in it.
But there's lots of good
training materials out there.
And if you just start, for example, Node,
you can run Javascript in your in your terminal
as well here, and you can get out of it
by pressing Ctrl+C two times.
So you will not be an expert
in the terminal overnight.
But it's something that you should be
thinking about because far too many good things
are happening in the terminal these days –
which is pretty bizarre
because it goes back to 1970's technology
when you think about it.
One other thing that we've
been using in the past
has been libraries and frameworks.
And, of course, there are
new frameworks every week.
All of them make our lives easier,
all of them are much better than plain JavaScript,
and some of them really,
really make a difference.
So be excited about them, look into them,
but always, always be aware
that being an expert in one version
of one framework for this month
might be an amazing skill set,
but in half a year's time,
it might not be a thing
that you need any longer.
So, to me, frameworks and libraries
are things that make our life easier
and are sometimes necessary
or sometimes really good for project work.
But being an expert in only one
of them might actually be a problem
in the near future if you're not flexible
enough to jump between frameworks
from time to time as well.
And knowing the underneath
technologies in JavaScript,
the language features that allow
these libraries to be what they are,
is a good skill set to have because then
you become independent of the library
that you want to and you just use
JavaScript and the library for the benefits
that it was written for.
The last thing I'm really excited about –
and I think a lot of people should use more
are online editors
or like playgrounds.
This is JSBin here, for example.
And JSBin is an opportunity for you
to write JavaScript, CSS, and HTML,
and execute it directly in the browser.
So in this case when I now have a div here
and I want to do something with it,
so in CSS, I can say the div
should be a background colour green,
and give it a width and height.
Then while I'm doing it, I already see
that there is a green div here right now.
And in JavaScript, I can now get
a reference to that.
And then you can say -
And if I use that one now
and I should run it,
then something should happen,
run with JS, and it turns
it into the other width,
although, in the CSS,
it has a width of 10 pixels.
These things are great
to try things out quickly
without having to set up anything
on your computer yourself.
Others, like CodePen also have
all kinds of, like, pre compilers in there.
So if you want to use SASS
or you want to use a lot of libraries like Vue.js,
or React without installing any of it,
these are great ways to try these things out.
They're also collaborative.
So other people can make a copy
of what you've done and change it around
and do something with them.
So there's three things
you can do with those.
Play with things, try them out, ask for help,
so when you have something that doesn't work
in your code, write a little demo
in one of those things and send that link around,
so people can actually edit them for you
or edit them with you collaboratively,
and then you can find the problem together
without having to describe what your problem is.
So these are great tools for teaching,
these are great tools for learning,
and these are great tools for just
collaborating with other people.
And when you use the preprocessors
and the settings that you can do
in these JavaScript tools here
where you can have all kind of precompilers
and all kind of different engines
that you can use, it means you don't have
to set up your computer, it means
you don't have to mess with your environment,
you just have something online
that you play with and if you like it,
then you can start
setting up your machine.
And this is where JavaScript
changed from the past.
We now have a whole ecosystem
of development tools to work with.
So to repeat, browsers are evergreen
and all of them come with developer tools,
so we should use these developer tools
and understand what their benefits are
rather than putting alerts or console logs
everywhere everywhere in our code.
Libraries and frameworks help us
to do things that are not as easy to be done
in native JavaScript, if you just
want to have something simply done,
they're probably a good idea,
but it might be dangerous to only rely on them.
Editor's are much better than the text editors
of the past because all of them are now integrated,
they're open, they're extensible,
and you can write code in them for them.
And online tools like JSBin and CodePen
are a great opportunity for you to try things out
without messing up your own computer
and to send things to other people
to collaboratively work on them.
So these are just a few of the things
where JavaScript works.
And the terminal is the last one where
we do a lot of, like, version controlling
and tooling in JavaScript itself.
Knowing all of these is quite a hassle
or is quite a job, but it will make you
much more effective, and you don't
need to be an expert in all of them.
You just need to try them out when
you need them and find some information online.
And that's what I wanted to talk
to you about in this video.
=======================
==   CLOSED CAPTIONS   ==
== BY YERKCOL PTY LTD ==
=======================