Welcome back. In this section
of Rediscovering JavaScript,
I want to talk about editor features
that we should be using
because they just make total sense.
We've always been very excited
that you just need a text editor
to write JavaScript
or even a command line if you wanted to.
But we have so many great tools these days
that make our life so much easier
and allow us to write predictable code,
maintainable code,
because the editor itself
has features in there for us.
For this example, we're going
to use Visual Studio Code,
which is an open-source editor by Microsoft.
You can also use Atom,
you can use all kinds of other editors.
Most frameworks
will have their own editors.
A lot of the features that we have
in these editors are the same
for all of these different tools.
So I just want to talk about
some of the features that you
might not have seen yet in these.
Not all of them are JavaScript-based.
Some of them will also
talk about HTML and CSS.
But as JavaScript is used
together with those technologies,
it does make sense
to think about them as well.
Now you get Visual Studio Code
by just going to code.visualStudio.com
And you can download it there.
You can download it for Mac,
Linux, or Windows,
so it's a cross-platform,
open-source, free editor
that you can just install on your machine
and it runs automatically from there.
It updates itself as well,
and you can sign in for, like,
getting the developer preview
if you want to really get excited about it.
There's also extensible documentation
about the editor itself, what it means,
how to use it, what kind
of features are coming,
what kind of features it has
for node.js and for JavaScript,
how to debug them, and how the feature sets
for different environments that you want to have.
These are constantly getting updated
and you can also edit them if you want to.
If you find something wrong in this documentation,
please edit them and send it back to the team
and you get features from that.
Now, a first thing to remember here,
or what's very important,
is that it's called Visual Studio Code,
but it's got nothing to do with Visual Studio.
Visual Studio is an IDE, that is,
most of the time,
for me as a JavaScript developer
overkill for what we're doing.
It has its benefits, of course,
for using in other languages.
It's a very great development environment.
But it's not Visual Studio.
So you don't need to worry about it
being a Microsoft product.
"You have to do everything with Microsoft."
This is an open-source product
that is maintained by Microsoft people
but also people from
the outside take part in that.
So a few things that I want to point out
that editors have nowadays that I think
are much more exciting
than what we had in the past.
First thing you see here is a colour scheme.
And this already helps me
in my code to see what is what.
So this is the document query selector,
and this here is a value, for example.
So you see in your code what is what.
That allows you to easily skim through
your code and understand what you're doing
rather than just having a black text
on white background
or white text on black background,
that you need to understand what is what.
The next thing these editors do
which is pretty amazing for you
is that you can change these to your needs.
So if you need, for example, a bigger font,
then you can change the font to it –
if you want a different font face,
you can have a different font face.
All of these things are tweakable.
So you can make this thing your
editor the best way you want to have it.
There's lots of settings in there.
There's lots of people writing their own themes.
There's a whole community around theming
of different editors and moving the theme
from one editor to another.
But all of these things are meant for you
to make your code more readable to yourself
and more readable to the next person
that has to maintain your code,
which actually might be
you in the near future.
The next thing that I love
about editors nowadays
is that they do automatically
things for you like indenting.
Like, for example, when you have
a new function here called "myFunction,"
and you do the brackets, you see that it
already indented into the next line,
that way making your code
much, much more readable.
There are automated settings there
and you could copy and paste a function in
or a piece of code in and it lays it out
for you the way you're supposed to do it.
And that's pretty powerful,
because in the past,
you had these these complaints
about one person using space,
one using one using tabs.
In this case, you can just define down here
if you want spaces or tabs
and you can change them around
to convert from spaces to tabs
and you can do the automated
indentation in this code for yourself.
So while you're writing code,
the syntax of the code,
or the look and feel of the code
is done for you by the editor, which, of course,
makes it much, much easier to be maintainable
and to make your code much more readable.
And you can concentrate
on writing your code
rather than styling
your code accordingly to that.
There are all kind of
interesting features there as well,
like when you have something like
an addEventListener here,
you can do a Command+D
to highlight all of them.
And as you can see,
we now have different cursors here.
So, instead of having one cursor,
you now have a cursor after each of them.
So if you want to rename all of them
to something else, you can do that
by just hitting delete and
renaming it to something else.
So that way, you don't have to do that
bit by bit and keep repeating things.
And when we repeat things, we make mistakes.
So this way, an editor helps you much,
much better to find out what's going on.
Autocompletion is something that
most editors have for you nowadays as well.
And this is very, very useful
because it does two things.
First of all, it makes sure
that you don't mistype things,
and second of all,
you type a lot less.
And a lot less typing means you can
write more code in less time,
and you also have
less strain on your fingers.
So for example, if I want to rewrite
that first line here, I start with a restart button,
and it realised already
I've got a restart button defined.
So all I have to type is rest or all the
other things that might be applicable to it.
So then, I just hit the tab completion,
and I have a restart button.
I then start the addEventListener,
and in this case, I could also
take the addEventListener
and highlight it, and that way,
I learned what add event listener means.
If I don't remember, for example,
the order of the parameters in this one
or I don't know what kind of features
are available to me – so in this case
is point up, touch start, point to cancel,
and so on and so forth,
I now know what these things are
just by clicking on them and
getting an autocompletion form yourself.
So this is what a good editor does for you
and it makes it much, much simpler
to write a lot more code
without doing any typos.
Now if you have a huge amount of code –
this is not too much of a huge amount of code.
It's just a simple game that I've written –
you can see that a good editor
has these maps here as well.
So you can jump in
the map itself to a certain part
rather than just
having to do it line by line.
So that's a nice little shortcut to jump
to a section in the code as well.
And it gives you an overview of, like,
how large the code is that you've written so far.
Another interesting thing is when you
have a big amount of code,
you sometimes wonder what something is
that you call and where it is.
So for example, I've got a
function here called "clearMove."
And it says here,
"Okay, does it define constant clearMove?"
And if I click on that one,
I can say "Peek Definition,"
and that way I can see where
the function is in the other part of the code.
So I don't have to scroll back and forth
between the two sections
to understand what I'm doing.
So I can just do this with a Ctrl+F12
or with a mouse here, and that way,
I can actually understand where I am.
So I can see this code is here,
the other code is here.
So I would have had to jump around
in the whole document just to do that peeking.
So these are some things
that are very, very powerful
to do in here when it
comes to writing JavaScript.
Other things that a good editor
should do for you is also allow you
to have several editors next to each other.
So in this case, I can split that here,
and I can have my HTML next to my JavaScript,
so I see how both of those interact
and I can jump between them.
One extra feature that
something like Visual Studio code has
is that it has the whole environment
that we talked about earlier –
the debugging and the console –
directly in one editor.
So you don't need to jump between the terminal
and the editor all the time because you have
an inbuilt terminal in the system here.
So I could just do my commands –
my build commands or my
version controlling commands –
directly in the editor
without having to jump
between the terminal
and my editor all the time.
Sometimes, it's a good thing to jump between
the two because you're changing your mind.
But it also is quite heavy
on your cognitive thinking
to go from one editor to another,
where it's like, if you stay in this one,
you can do all the commands
that you need to do here,
so you can do your version controlling,
you can do your build scripts,
and all of those could
(ought) to be automated.
So every time I save
something in the editor,
it would do automatically part of my build
script
or part of my deployment for me.
So that way, you have everything in one editor.
This is also great if you teach people
something about web development,
you can just give them this one editor
rather than saying like,
"You need an editor, and you need to set up
your terminal, you need to install your terminal that way."
Another thing that it does is linting.
So if, for example, you have your CSS here,
and I've got a linter installed,
if I have it show the problems,
it should tell me when something goes wrong.
So you can see here – now I have
a semi-colon that I deleted.
And all of a sudden, the
background here becomes red,
and I've got squiggly lines
under those things.
That's much like when you do a typo in Word,
it does it now inside the code.
So in this case, I forgot the semicolon
which is now an error here,
It's "semi-colon expected."
And then the rest of the CSS selector
is also broken because the semi-colon isn't there.
So if I now put the semi-colon in there again,
then all of these errors are going away.
So that way, I get insight directly,
while I'm coding that I'm doing something wrong,
rather than having to go to the browser,
debug it and find my problems that way.
You can do the same thing in JavaScript
by either installing an extension
or you can also use –
just do a comment above
your JavaScript called //@ts-check
That one uses TypeScript's linter
to run your JavaScript against.
So in this case, it now shows me
all the JavaScript errors
that I made in this one,
and some of them
are actually not really errors,
but they're false positives.
But if I made some mistake,
it will automatically tell me that.
So for example, if I deleted that game here,
and I tried to access the game somewhere else,
it says cannot find game.
So in this case, I have
not defined the game,
so I cannot actually do
a game turns because they don't exist.
That would be an error that the browser
would throw at me, and I would have to debug there.
But as I have to linter turned on
in the editor itself,
it shows me the things
while I'm coding it,
and that way, I become a better developer
because I don't make mistakes.
You also see the red dots here.
These are telling us where all
the problems are that we just talked about.
So some of them have these issues
and you roll over the squiggly line,
and then it tells you what the problem is.
The last thing that is great in this editor
is that it has version controlling built in.
And we're going to talk
about version control later.
So when you change something
and you click on it, you can actually see
the differences in your merging.
So in this case, if I want to send this back
to the server, it tells me now that these
new two lines have been added,
and these two lines
have been deleted,
and the game thing
has been changed here as well.
So I get – before I send something
to the server or to my colleagues,
it tells me all the things that happened.
So in essence, a good editor
should tell you –
should make it, first of all,
easy for you to write,
by having a nice theme and making it easier
to type things by having autocompletion
and the indentation and these things for you.
And the extra bits that I love
about Visual Studio Code
and others as well is that
it has the terminal built in,
it has the linting built in,
and it tells me
when I'm doing something wrong
while I'm doing something wrong
rather than me having to find out by trying it
in the browser and then breaking it.
So think about setting up
your editor for yourself.
And if you choose to use a Visual Studio Code,
you know it's an open-source editor
and it will not go away.
And that's a great thing too.
So now you know how a good editor
can make you a better developer.
And finding the extensions for it is actually
something to make it your editor as well.
Next, I want to talk about something
that is very important when you want to work
with a lot of other people
and also when you want to make sure
that what you've done today
is understandable in three weeks time,
and that's version controlling.
=======================
==   CLOSED CAPTIONS   ==
== BY YERKCOL PTY LTD ==
=======================