As somebody who's learned
JavaScript a long time ago
who actually is pretty
much old-school about it,
you might think JavaScript is something
that you just put into HTML pages
to make them more interactive
and to do something like loading up
something in the background
or downloading something in the background
or making something more interactive.
JavaScript has moved past
that quite some time ago.
When HTML5 became a specification,
all of a sudden, the HTML stack
became something that is more dependent
on JavaScript than before,
because some of the features that
we needed didn't make any sense without it.
A canvas element doesn't
do anything – it's just a canvas.
That's what's actually
implied in the name.
So you needed JavaScript
to do something with that.
Some of the other features of JavaScript
have gone the same way.
So the idea of having a text editor
and writing something in an HTML page
and opening it in the browser
just to have JavaScript
is pretty much old-school
and you should be thinking
about it more as a platform
or as an environment
to build something with.
If you take a look around the web
and see what JavaScript is doing
right now, there's manifold things.
There are all kinds of things
that we do with JavaScript.
And you might not be aware
of what's going on there.
Take, for example, something like three.js
three.js is a 3D library that allows you
to do 3D animations in JavaScript,
something that, in the past,
we always used Flash for.
So JavaScript is a language now
that is used for highly creative things
rather than just something
that is on the web to make it prettier
or to make an animated text
in the background scrolling around.
Things we've done
in with Flash in the past
are now firmly in the space
of JavaScript because JavaScript
is supported in all the browsers
and doesn't need to be downloaded
and doesn't need to be installed
like Flash used to be,
QuickTime used to be,
or even Silverlight used to be.
Other things that JavaScript
is doing are actually becoming
a part of your day-to-day life.
Slack, for example, is probably a tool
that you've been using,
and Slack is written in JavaScript
with HTML and CSS
as the other two technologies.
So, in essence, what we have
with Slack is an application
that would run in the browser
packaged up in an installer
so you can use them on the desktop,
on your mobile phone, and everywhere else.
The platform this is
based on is called Electron.
And Electron allows you to write
JavaScript and HTML and CSS
and then package it up as an application
to get it installed on your operating systems
and on the different mobile platforms.
So JavaScript written for Electron
is much more likely to be easier
for some developers to do
because you don't have that unknown
of which browser
it's gonna run in.
You don't have the issue of your end users
being able to turn things on and off
because you control the code
and you also control the distribution
and the install process
in the operating systems themselves.
One big change in the JavaScript space
was when Node came out.
Node is a server-side version
of JavaScript where you can write anything
that you used to write in things like Java,
PHP, or Python - now in JavaScript itself.
So what node allows you to do
is write servers, is run your microservices,
write anything that you
wanted to have in these older
much more complex
languages now in JavaScript.
Node is installable
on every platform out there.
And you will, in most cases,
want to have Node installed
because the tooling of JavaScript
are written in Node
and which allow you to be much
more effective as a JavaScript developer
is something to be really excited
about and something to use.
Now, as Node is server-side
and Node is a different way of writing code,
the rules applying for being
a JavaScript developer in Node
are different than being a JavaScript
developer that writes things for the web.
So don't get too frustrated
if you don't understand this
and you don't want
to get into that space.
But there are still many things in Node
that are very effective
and make it much more effective to use.
NPM is the package manager of JavaScript.
So Node solutions are now written in packages
and then can be installed as packages
in your operating systems
or also used as packages in your other code.
As somebody who is old-school JavaScript
like me, this sounds very complex.
And to a degree, it is.
But as somebody coming
from the Perl world or a Java world,
this is a very simple
and normal way of development.
So what we have with NPM and Node
is JavaScript leavening up
to becoming a real software platform
to write huge applications in
and to build huge applications
put together by reusable components.
As people were writing
massive applications in JavaScript,
the language showed some of its problems.
The nature of JavaScript
that it doesn't have any "types"
made it hard for people
who came from other languages
to write thousands and thousands
of lines of JavaScript
and be able to refactor them later on.
Typescript solves that problem
by putting a type system
on top of JavaScript, and that way
makes it much more scalable
and much, much easier to refactor.
So, if you write huge applications
in JavaScript, probably Typescript
is a good idea to think about.
And Typescript also has the benefit
of being stricter in its syntax
than JavaScript is, so you can use
the Typescript linter – later on,
we're gonna do this in another video –
to show you what your JavaScript errors are
while you're actually writing them.
I don't want you to get discouraged
by looking at all these tools
and thinking now,
"Oh, my God, I have to understand all of them."
These are different options
of where JavaScript is being used
and where you can become
a JavaScript developer
or can relearn being a JavaScript developer.
Not everybody has to become a Node developer
or has to use Electron to build applications.
You can still use JavaScript
to build normal websites
and to package them up in other ways
or not touch the server-side at all.
So what JavaScript is, because of its
versatility as a language, it's a "pick and mix".
It's like you take the things
that you want to use and, career-wise,
I would actually advise people
to find one thing that really gets you excited
and concentrate on that one
rather than being a jack-of-all-trades
and hoping you have enough time
to keep up with all these different implementations,
because most likely,
you will not have that time.
In the next video, we're going to talk
about some of the options
that you have to become a JavaScript developer
or sometimes you don't really want
to write JavaScript itself but use
something else that makes you more effective.
=======================
==   CLOSED CAPTIONS   ==
== BY YERKCOL PTY LTD ==
=======================